<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-dahm-tacacs-security-00"
    submissionType="IETF">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="TACACS+ TLS">
            TACACS+ TLS Support
        </title>

        <author fullname="Thorsten Dahm" initials="T." surname="Dahm">
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street></street>
                    <code></code>
                    <city></city>
                    <country></country>
                </postal>
                <email>thorsten.dahm@gmail.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Douglas Gash" initials="D." surname="Gash">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street></street>
                    <code></code>
                    <city></city>
                    <country></country>
                </postal>
                <email>dcmgash@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Andrej Ota" initials="A." surname="Ota">
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street></street>
                    <code></code>
                    <city></city>
                    <country></country>
                </postal>
                <email>andrej@ota.si</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date />
        <area>Operations and Management Area (ops)</area>
        <workgroup>Operations and Management Area Working Group</workgroup>

        <keyword>TACACS+</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
		The <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref> provides device administration for routers, network access servers and other networked computing devices via one or more centralized servers.
                This document, a companion to <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ protocol</xref>, adds Transport Layer Security (<xref target="RFC8446">TLS</xref>) support and deprecates former inferior security mechanisms.
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
		The <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref> provides device administration for routers, network access servers and other networked computing devices via one or more centralized servers.
		The protocol carries authentication, authorization and accounting information for TACACS+ clients.
		While this information is highly sensitive, TACACS+ lacks modern and/or effective confidentiality, integrity, and authentication of the connection and network traffic between the server and client.
            </t>
            <t>
		The existing confidentiality, integrity, and authentication mechanisms of TACACS+ are extremely weak.
		The Security Considerations section of <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref> adequately describes this and will not be repeated.
            </t>
            <t>
		To address these flaws, this document updates the <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref> to support <xref target="RFC8446">TLS</xref> authentication and encryption, and deprecates the use of its former mechanisms.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Technical Definitions">
            <t>
		The Technical Definitions section of <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref> is fully applicable here and will not be repeated.  The following terms are also used in this document.
            </t>
            <t>
		Peer
            </t>
            <t>
		This refers to a TACACS+ Server or Client.
            </t>
            <t>
		Session
            </t>
            <t>
		Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+</xref> as a single authentication sequence, a single authorization exchange, or a single accounting exchange.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="TLS for TACACS+">
            <t>
		TACACS+ connections are over TCP/IP, initiated by the Client to the Server.
		The well-known TCP/IP port 49 on the Server is used for unencrypted and encrypted connections as defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+</xref>.
		A connection may be used for only a single Session or the multiplexing of multiple Sessions.
            </t>
            <t>
		It is mandatory to maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and authentication of these connections, as <xref target="RFC3365">RFC3365</xref> dictates the need for end-to-end security.
		The current IETF technology best suited for TACACS+ is TLS, which can provide both authentication and transport encryption.
            </t>
            <section title="Well-Known TCP/IP Port" anchor="wellknown">
	    <t>
		All data exchanged by TACACS+ Peers MUST be encrypted, including the authentication of the Peers.
		Therefore, encryption MUST be initiated immediately upon the establishment of the TCP/IP connection.
		For this reason, it is desirable to not use a "STARTTLS" command process that is a feature of some protocols, that once existed without TLS, use to maintain backward compatibility.
		Instead, a different well-known TCP/IP port is assigned, port [TBD].
	    </t>
	    <t>
		A new port is considered appropriate and superior to "STARTTLS" because it allows for:
		<list style="symbols">
		<t>easily blocking the unencrypted or inferiorly encrypted version by the port number,</t>
		<t>a passive Intrusion Detection System (IDS) can watch the unencrypted version,</t>
		<t>STARTTLS can be vulnerable to Man in the Middle (MitM) attacks,</t>
		<t>and can help prevent the accidental exposure of sensitive information due to misconfiguration.</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
	    <t>
		However, co-existence of inferior authentication and encryption, whether TACACS+ legacy or deprecated parts that compose TLS, presents opportunity for down-grade attacks.
		The simplest way to address the exposure from TACACS+ legacy methods is to refuse legacy TACACS+ connections at the server entirely, perhaps using separate servers for legay and TLS.
		Another approach is to have configuration of TACACS+ servers on clients require TLS and likewise server's configuration of permitted clients.
		Furthermore, Peers SHOULD be configurable to limit offered or recognized TLS versions and algorithms to those recommended.
	    </t>
	    <t>
XXX any other issues?
	    </t>
            </section>
	    <section title="TLS Protocol Version">
            <t>
		TACACS+ implementations supporting TLS encryption MUST implement at least <xref target="RFC5246">TLS version 1.2</xref>.
		However, they SHOULD also implement newer TLS versions as they emerge and MUST abandon TLS versions as they are deprecated, including TLS 1.2 and prior versions.
XXX They SHOULD implement <xref target="RFC8446">TLS version 1.3</xref>.
            </t>
            </section>
	    <section title="Cypher Requirements">
            <t>
		TACACS+ Servers supporting TLS MUST utilise the TLS encryption options described in the following sections.
XXX but should be allowed to evolve as TLS does.
            </t>
		<section title="Mandatory Cipher Suites">
		<t>
		<xref target="RFC5246">TLS 1.2</xref> allows specifying application profiles prescribing which cipher suites to implement for interoperability purposes.
		To maintain simplicity of current TACACS+ configuration using pre-shared secrets, the server implementation MUST implement:
		<list style="symbols">
		<t>TLS-DHE-PSK-WITH-AES-128-GCM-SHA256</t>
		<t>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</t>
		<t>TLS_DHE_PSK_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA</t>
		</list>
		</t>
		<t>
		A Client MUST implement at least one of the cipher suites which are implemented on the Server, and MAY implement all of them.
		</t>
		<t>
		Both Clients and Servers MAY implement other cipher suites, but their interoperability is not guaranteed and their implementation is outside of scope of this document.
		XXX again; should allow a way to evolve.  how???
		</t>
		</section>
            </section>
	    <section title="Authentication">
            <t>
XXX
            </t>
		<section title="PSK Identity Requirements">
		<t>
Because determining a correct PSK value on the server side is a computationally intensive operation requiring multiple round trips, a mechanism for hitless key change must be defined.
During TLS handshake, a client MUST use PSK identity as defined in <xref target="RFC4279"/> to signal to the server which PSK value to use.
If server does not recognize PSK identity it MUST respond with decrypt_error alert and MUST NOT respond with unknown_psk_identity.
</t>
<t>
Process to change pre-shared keys on server and client is then:
<list style="format %d">
<t>Add new key with new PSK identity on the server.</t>
<t>Add new key with new PSK identity on the client.</t>
<t>Remove old key with old PSK identity from the client.</t>
<t>Remove old key with old PSK identity from the server.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Note: PSK identity is transmitted in clear text and must not contain information which could aid an attacker who can eavesdrop on the connection.
		</t>
		</section>
		<section title="TLS Certificate Identity Requirements">
		<t>
XXX
		</t>
		</section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Deprecation of TACACS+ PSK and Encryption">
            <t>
		The original TACACS+ draft specified a form of encryption and Peer authentication using a pre-shared key that is wholly inadequate by modern standards and is diminutively referred to as data obfuscation in <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref>.
		The introduction of TLS PSK and certificate Peer authentication and TLS encryption to TACACS+ obsolesces these former mechanisms and so are hereby deprecated.
		Along with them, the TAC_PLUS_UNENCRYPTED_FLAG flag in the TACACS+ header, the least significant bit (LSB) of the flags field, is also deprecated.
            </t>
            <t>
		Peers compliant with this document and using TLS should set the TAC_PLUS_UNENCRYPTED_FLAG flag in the Packet header, indicating that the data obfuscation is not used.
		A Peer that receives a Packet without the flag set, should immediately terminate the TCP/IP connection.
            </t>
            <t>
		A Client that is compliant with this document MUST NOT utilize these deprecated authentication or encryption methods with a Server that is also compliant.
		A TACACS+ implementation MAY, and is encouraged to, offer a configuration mechanism to disable them.
            </t>
            <t>
		A future document SHOULD be written to deprecate the well-known TCP/IP port 49, allocated by <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs">TACACS+ Protocol</xref>.
            </t>
        </section>

       <section title="Security Considerations">
           <t>
		This document improves the confidentiality, integrity, and authentication of the connection and network traffic between the TACACS+ Peers by adding TLS support.
		This does not in itself protect the server nor clients; the operator and equipment vendors have a role.
		That role is to diligently follow current best practices for maintaining the integrity of network devices and selection of TLS key and encryption algorithms.
            </t>
	    <t>
		It is not and never will be reasonable to expect RFCs be updated in perpetuity as each new TLS version and/or algorithm emerges nor at a rate to keep pace.
		It would be highly desirable for the TLS working group to publish a document that evolves with TLS and its algorithms that RFCs such as this one could reference without the need to update those RFCs, thus allowing them to evolve by inheritance.
		As no such document exists, implementers and operators SHOULD make informed use of RFCs to determine which TLS versions and algorithms should be supported, deprecated, or abandoned, in the absence of updates to this RFC.
            </t>
            <t>
		TLS encryption SHOULD be used in deployments when both the clients and servers support it.
		Servers that support TLS encryption MAY be configured to allow legacy encryption when TLS encryption is not supported by the client.
		However, operators must be cognizant of the threat of a downgrade attack, as described in <xref target="wellknown"/>.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		It is NOT RECOMMENDED to deploy TACACS+ without TLS transport or legacy encryption, except for test and debug environments.
	    </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
		The authors request that, when this draft is accepted by the working group, the OPSAWG Chairs submit a request to IANA for an early allocation, per <xref target="RFC4020">RFC402</xref>, of a new well-known system TCP/IP port number for "tacacss", described as "TACACS+ over TLS/SSL".
		The name "tacacss" follows the common practice of appending an "s" to the name given to the non-TLS well-known port.
            </t>
            <t>
		RFC EDITOR: this port number should be replace "[TBD]" within this document.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The author(s) would like to thank Russ Housley, Steven M. Bellovin, and Stephen Farrell for their support, insightful review, and/or comments.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4279"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-opsawg-tacacs.xml"?>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3365"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4020"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6335"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7605"?>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
